what we have discussed so far are the
so-called flat page tables where for
every page number there is an entry in
the table let's talk about the size of
such a flat page table it has one entry
per page in the entire virtual address
space even four pages in the address
space that the program never actually
accesses such as those pages that sit
between the heap and the stack the entry
in such a page table contains the frame
number plus a few bits that tell us if
the page is accessible for example the
protection bits or a bit that tells us
that the page is not really in physical
memory at all so the entry in the page
table is typically similar in size to
the actual physical address the entry
needs to contain the frame number which
is most of the bits in the physical
address it doesn't need to contain the
page offset that the physical address
has but it needs to contain some extra
bits so overall if we have a 32 bit
physical address probably the entry size
in the page table will be 32 bits if we
have a 64 bit physical address probably
the entry size will be 64 bits so the
overall size of a page table is the
overall size of the virtual memory of a
process divided by the page size this is
how many entries we have in the page
table times the size of a page table
entry let's look at an example where the
virtual memory size is 4 gigabytes for a
process the page size is 4 kilobytes and
the size of an entry is 4 bytes in that
case we get a 4 megabyte page table per
process now note that a process might
actually be using less than 4 megabytes
of actual virtual memory because most of
the pages are unused in such a process
yet the page table still needs to be 4
megabytes so one problem with the flat
page tables is that the page table is
reasonably large even if the process
uses very little of its available
virtual memory the other problem with
the flat page table is that if the
virtual memory is a 64-bit address space
so if the virtual memory is 2 to the
64th bytes then we are
talking about the page table that is
four billion times this which is much
larger than the memory we actually have
so the page table like this simply
cannot fit in memory if we have a large
virtual address space and today's
processors have such a large space so we
need to reorganize the page table so
that it doesn't occupy this much space